A Guide to the Papers of Edward F. Hewins 1856-1957
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Edward F. Hewins Papers 1856-1957
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 26
1 Hollinger Documents Case
Gift of Mr. Edward F. Hewins, March 10, 1978
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
The man, around whom the Edward F. Hewins Papers are organized, is the donor's father, Captain Charles E. Hewins. Charles Hewins was born in Dorchester, Mass., September 2, 1841 and was the second of six children born to John and Charlotte Hewins. Volunteering at the beginning of the Civil War in the Union Army, Hewins was enrolled in Company I, 42nd Massachusetts Infantry. Hewins served in Company I until January 1863 when he was taken prisoner at Galveston, Texas. During this same year, Charles' oldest brother William was killed at the Battle of Chancellorsville. Charles however, was fortunately paroled after a short confinement in a prisoner of war camp. After a prisoner exchange was arranged at New Orleans, Hewins returned for a brief period to his home in Dorchester and then came to Fort Monroe near the close of the Civil War. While stationed at Fort Monroe, Hewins and his friend Albert Howe served under Captain Charles Wilder in the Freedman's Bureau. Following the war, both Hewins and Howe began collaborating in the general mercantile business in Hampton, Virginia.
A few years later, Charles Hewins began developing his business interests in oyster planting and harvesting. He remained in the oyster field for the rest of his life, and during the first year of business, owned and sailed two vessels, The Independence and The Farmer's Return. As one of the pioneer oyster planters of Virginia, Hewins held oyster grounds at Ballast Marsh and Hampton Bar.
On March 31, 1891 Charles Hewins married Mary E. Coats of New York state, at the time a teacher at the Hampton Institute. They resided until his death in the home that he had built on a tract of land purchased from the former Bates Estate.
Charles Hewins was active in community affairs and was a member of St. Tammany Lodge No. 5, A.F. & A.M., and of the Hampton Commandry, Knights Templar. In 1927 Hewins suffered a stroke of paralysis and died several months later, at the age of 86.
Among those who survived Charles Hewins was his only son, Edward F. Hewins. Edward Hewins was born in 1893 in Hampton, Virginia and is the donor of the Hewins Papers to the Old Dominion University Department of Archives and Manuscripts. Educated at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Edward Hewins achieved prominence in the Tidewater area as a marine architect at the Newport News Shipbuilding Drydock Company. As was his father, he was active in local civic organizations until well advanced in years.
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of Edward F. Hewins contains family papers relating primarily to the donor's father Captain Charles E. Hewins (1841-1927). The collection is arranged into three series according to content: Correspondence, Civil War Military Papers, Miscellaneous.
By far the highlight of the collection is Series I in which family correspondence is well represented for the period 1862 through Reconstruction. Numerous historical references to the Civil War period, such as the Lincoln Assassination and Sherman's southern campaign, are found in the letters written by Charles Hewins. In this first subseries, are also several letters written while Hewins was a prisoner of war, describing both the camp at New Orleans and the Battle of Galveston in 1863. The Hewins letters additionally provide an interesting perspective on secessionist activities and social attitudes toward the Black "freedman", as viewed through a Unionist's eyes.
Incoming correspondence to Charles Hewins from family and business friends completes the first series. Signing her letters as "C.A. Hewins", Charles' mother is the most frequent contributor. Providing family news along with comments on local affairs, these and similar accounts from the remaining letters allow for a balanced overview of social conditions in the North and the South during the same historical period.
Series II contains photocopies from the National Archives and the US Bureau of Interior. In both cases, these copies deal with the military record of Charles Hewins. Under Series III are grouped a small number of miscellaneous materials, among which is a brief genealogical chart of the Hewins family in the hand of Edward F. Hewins.
The nature of the documents in the collection vary according to their physical state and provenance. In most cases, the items are original holographs and their entries in the finding aid are designated with the letter "H". A relatively large number of the letters, however, are photocopies of original letters. Because of their physical deterioration in many cases, these documents have been grouped by year instead of assigned an item by item entry. Also grouped by year are brief summaries of original correspondence. The synopses as well as the copies were made by Mrs. Gladys Blair, a former graduate student in History at Old Dominion University. Accordingly, these documents are designated in the finding aid with either the letter "C" or "S".
Arrangement
The nature of the documents in the collection vary according to their physical state and provenance. In most cases, the items are original holographs and their entries in the finding aid are designated with the letter "H". A relatively large number of the letters, however, are photocopies of original letters. Because of their physical deterioration in many cases, these documents have been grouped by year instead of assigned an item by item entry. Also grouped by year are brief summaries of original correspondence. The synopses as well as the copies were made by Mrs. Gladys Blair, a former graduate student in History at Old Dominion University. Accordingly, these documents are designated in the finding aid with either the letter "C" or "S".
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Charles E. Hewins - outgoing
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins (Mother): (H) June 1, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) September 23, 1867 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) March 13, 1868 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (C) - five letters 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (C) - six letters 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (C) - three letters 1866 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (C) - four letters 1867 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (S) - three letters 1862, 1863, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mr. John C. Hewins: (C) 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Charlotte Hewins: (S) - three letters 1862, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Helen Hewins: (S) March 5, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Susie Hewins: (H) June 15, 1866 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Susie Hewins: (C) June 21, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Susie Hewins: (S) February 27, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Charles E. Hewins - incoming (family)
    - Lillian H. Gay: (H) November 21, 1926 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) June 12, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) June 30, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) August 21, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) September 11, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) October 2, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) December 14, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) December 25, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) January 18, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) January 22, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) February 12, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) August 13, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) September 2, 1866 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) February 3, 1867 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) August 5, 1867 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) September 8, 1867 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) October 22, 1868 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) May 9, 1868 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Mrs. C.A. Hewins: (H) November 14, 1869 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Helen Hewins:(H) January 1, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 35)
    - John Foster Hewins:(H) March 30, c. 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 36)
    - John Foster Hewins:(H) February 4, 1894 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Richard Hewins:(H) May 24, 1876 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Susie Hewins:(H) May 29, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Susie Hewins:(H) July 22, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Susie Hewins:(H) October 30, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Susie Hewins:(H) February 5, 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Susie Hewins:(H) January 2, 1869 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Captain Charles B. Wilder:(H) November, 1880 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Charles E. Hewins - incoming (friends and business)
    - Clarence (?):(H) July 10, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 45)
    - George G. French:(H) February 25, 1877 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 46)
    - George G. French:(H) July 17, 1877 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 47)
    - George G. French:(H) June 20, 1878 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Albert Howe:(H) August 6, 1877 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 49)
    - J.A. Lowe:(H) February 4, 1869 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Increase S. Smith:(H) December 30, 1857 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Family Correspondence
    - Edward F. Hewins to Aberdeen W. Child: (encl. letter 9/20/41; bill 1/12/42, photograph 6/14/41) c. January 6, 1857 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Mrs. Charles B. Wilder to Mrs. C.A. Hewins:(C) February 22, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 53)
- Civil War Military Papers - Charles E. Hewins
  - Civil War Company Muster Role: (C) National Archives 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Civil War Prisoner of War Record: (C) National Archives 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Charles E. Hewins Pension File: (C) US Bureau of the Interior (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 56)
- Miscellaneous
  - Order of Exercises at the Gibson Grammar School March 24, 1856 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Newspaper obituaries for Charles E. Hewins 1927 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hewins family genealogical chart:(H) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Calling cards: Lucia F.M. Fenner, Dr. & Mrs. Boutelle (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 60)